Guide to the Jim McGinty Papers AIA.058
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jim McGinty Papers
1949-2010
1978-2001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
McGinty, Jim, 1937-2010
AIA.058
1.5 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
Jim McGinty (1937-2010) was a teacher and an active member in the Irish traditional music community in both the United States and Ireland. He was a member of the Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann (The Association of Traditional Irish Musicians) North America and the Michael Coleman Branch of Comhaltas. The Jim McGinty Papers document McGinty's participation in Comhaltas and Fleadh Cheoil na hÉireann, as well as his work as a high school teacher and coach. The collection dates from 1949 to 2010, with the bulk of material dating between 1978 and 2001, and includes programs, schedules, newsletters, date books, clippings, periodicals, administrative documents, and correspondence.
Scope and Contents
The Jim McGinty Papers document McGinty's participation in traditional Irish music organizations, and his work as a high school teacher and coach. The collection dates from 1949 to 2010, with the bulk of material dating between 1978 and 2001, and includes programs, schedules, newsletters, date books, clippings, periodicals, administrative documents, and correspondence. The bulk of the material documents McGinty's participation in Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann (The Association of Traditional Irish Musicians) North America, the Michael Coleman Branch of Comhaltas, and Comhaltas's Fleadh Cheoil na hÉireann from 1978 through 2002. This material consists of event programs, schedules, and qualifier and result lists for competitions. There is a small amount of correspondence, financial documents, and membership reports regarding the Michael Coleman Branch in the 1980s and 1990s. McGinty's work as a teacher and coach is documented through a small amount of clippings and certificates from the 1970s through the 1990s. The collection also contains photographs of McGinty with family and friends at various events in the United States and Ireland, and McGinty's date books from 1977 to 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Barbara McGinty in 2010. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.056.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by organization title or format of material.
Biographical Note
Jim McGinty (1937-2010) was a teacher and an active member in the Irish traditional music community in both the United States and Ireland. He worked for over 30 years as a special education teacher and coached a number of sports teams in the North Rockland School District in New York state. He was a member of the Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann (The Association of Traditional Irish Musicians) North America and the Michael Coleman Branch of Comhaltas. He served as the chairman of the branch a number of times in the 1990s. He was active in Comhaltas's Fleadh Cheoil na hÉireann, and encouraged similar festivals in the United States. He hosted an Irish music radio program for over two decades for the American Irish Association on WVOX in the New York City and Westchester County areas.
Separated Materials
Approximately 550 sound recordings on compact disc were transferred to the Avery Fisher Center in 2010. Approximately 150 sound recordings on disc were transferred to the Avery Fisher Center in July 2018.
Irish -- Music.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish -- Societies, etc.; Programs (documents); Datebooks.; Comhaltas Ceolótirí Éireann; Comhaltas Ceolótirí Éireann. Fleadh Cheoil Na hÉireann
- Award, business cards, and patch, 1960-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1949-2004 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
- Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann -- Fleadh Cheoil Na hÉireann, 1977-2003 (Box 1, Folder 12-18, Box 2, Folder 1-6, Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann -- General, 1970-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5-11)
- Comhaltas Ceoltóirí Éireann -- Michael Coleman Branch, 1978-2004 (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
- Correspondence, 1962-2007 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Datebooks, 1979-2008 (Box 3, Folder 9-13, Box 4, Folder 1)
- Irish music events programs, 1983-2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Periodicals, 1974-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1969-2010 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)